Welcome [music] everyone. We're here
with Vanessa Parley who is the managing
director at Stanford HAI and is integral
in running the uh HAI index AI index and
it's been going on for years. I think it
even predates HAI. HAI I think is one of
five units of Stanford. Uh seven or
eight years ago the university said AI
is going to be a big deal. we got to do
a cross uh campus um initiative and
create this institute and as far as I'm
concerned a key element of that
institute is the gathering of the
information compiling it and sending it
out and and you do a road show every
April you go to different continents to
kind of spread the word and it's it's a
document that really helps inform people
where things are going where they've
come from and where they could go and
there are a lot of questions AI is not
just this nice technology uh you know to
wave at at a museum. It's it's going to
change how as a species we interact and
how we reach our potential. And here in
conversations action, Alex and I are
going to interview Vanessa uh about you
know some of the trends she's seeing and
uh um you know we're going to get into
it. Uh so Vanessa, thank you for joining
us.
>> Yeah, thanks for having me.
>> All right, welcome to the CIA.
So, HAI, this is related, refresh my
memory, this is related to the Stanford
initiative to do an annual report on AI
progress for about a hundred years,
something like that.
>> So, there's actually two reports. So,
there's the AI 100, which comes out
every 5 years, September or Yeah, it's
coming out soon.
>> It's like a millennium in AI.
>> Exactly. And so, the AI 100 came first.
They realized, oh, actually, this
technology is moving super fast. every
five years is too long. And so the AI
index spun out of the AI 100 and the AI
index is an annual report which even now
seems too long. But um yes, as John
mentioned, it's it's meant to get give a
datadriven view of the state of AI um to
cut through the hype we see every day.
We have a lot of um data and trends to
try to get ground people in like what is
actually happening. So I think one of
several elephants in the room in an era
when there is day-to-day progress what
is the point of an annual report?
>> Uh perspective I would say most
importantly um and I mean even last year
right we see one of the aspects we cover
in the report is benchmarks. So these
evaluations of how AI is performing
across different types of tasks. Um and
every year we incorporate new benchmarks
because the benchmarks from the prior
year uh AI models have have surpassed
human capability. Um but that in itself
is um something to to learn from is what
are these benchmarks really measuring?
If we just create new ones every
6 months when AI surpasses whatever
maybe arbitrary test we have decided um
we should measure the system against.
And so one of the things that we talk
about is this field of benchmarking
itself probably needs to be rethought
and reconsidered now that AI is out of
the lab into the real world and moving
so quickly. So maybe to develop this a
bit
>> in hugging fa and it's in hugging face
>> maybe maybe not scandal duour. So I I
think second elephant in the room is the
benchmarks themselves. There has been
recent set of revelations including in
connection with one of my favorite at
least historic benchmarks uh which is
from Epic Frontier Math Tier 4 that the
benchmarks themselves are broken and
that if you fix the benchmarks it turns
out that they're all essentially
saturated at this point by the Frontier
models and the the wave of
shock and awe if you will spreading from
Frontier Math to tier 4 now version two
to other benchmarks
discovering that actually the reason
that all of these otherwise quite
challenging benchmarks aren't at 100% is
because the definitions were wrong and
the benchmarks were broken. How do you
deal with that? Are you at all concerned
maybe more specific question that the
benchmarks maybe you're ensembling them
the benchmarks themselves are
unintentionally sandbagging all the
performance and at this point the
benchmarks themselves are cooked.
>> Yes. So exactly we know that there are
many flaws in these benchmarks. Um they
were developed um when AI was still
being researched in labs. Imageet was
developed in 2012 to figure out how well
AI systems can identify images. Um the
benefit of benchmarks is it creates a
goal for research to go in. Um and so
they have historically been able to push
research forward in certain directions.
Um that said, the AI models are now out
of research labs and in the real world.
Um and we do it's a call to action. We
need to figure out a better way to
really evaluate how these models perform
and how we maybe benchmarking isn't
right, but at the very least how we
define these benchmarks. Um and and
there are researchers that I'm working
with at Stanford thinking about this.
How do we dis how do we develop um a
science of measurement um that can
actually predict how well these systems
uh perform when they're deployed in real
world scenarios because right now if a
if a model can pass the MCAT that does
not make it a good doctor and so is that
really the right benchmark
>> so arguendo maybe there are several
pieces of one very large elephant in the
the room historically there are a lot of
it's a it's a very big room with maybe
one very big elephant. The the challenge
is there's an enormous cottage industry
of evaluators of benchmarkers on the one
hand. On the other hand, things are
moving so quickly now. An annual report
I I think is sort of it's hopeless to
keep up even if the goal is to put maybe
an impromater of Stanford or or some
other trusted institution on it. So, let
me ask the question this way. if your
program which as I understand it this is
a Stanford funded program
>> uh so it's run by Stanford it is led by
a group of folks internal and external
from industry academia and policy and
others
>> coalition coalition so if someone wrote
you a check for a billion dollars and
said do something far more ambitious
with your time benchmarking it's taken
care of already there are lots of
benchmarks out there averaging
benchmarks producing a regular report
the AI can produce a regular report on
itself at this point. Recursive
self-improvement is here. The AI is
improving day by day. AI, you know, put
put any task in front of it, including
being a good doctor and AI is either
superhuman already or is just
extrapolating by the law of straight
lines about to be superhuman. How do you
as a program within Stanford or a
coalition, how do you solve the problem
of obsolescence? Just to put it baldly,
are you worried about obsolescence?
>> Um, so since the index was launched in
2017, uh, a lot has changed. Um,
>> yes.
>> And there are many other organizations
putting out similar types of reports to
your point like AI can do a lot of the
report making now. Um
but I do think that there is value in um
an independent organization with the
oversight of people from various
different industries putting out
information that is datadriven neutral
and comprehensive in the way that the
index is. Now the index if we completely
rethought the index and put out
something like that that provides a
datadriven view of something
>> you have to start over someone with a
billion dollars some generous donor
benefactor says here's a billion dollars
what you were working on previously it's
cooked it'sion dollars of tokens
>> a billion well billion tokens doesn't
buy buys you a cup of coffee at this
point uh gives you a billion US dollars
and says all right what you were doing
previously can be automated you can work
on something more ambitious Now, what do
you work on?
>> Yeah. Um, so I argue that it can't not
all of it can be automated. I again, I
still think that there's value in a
datadriven uh view of what's going on.
Perhaps more frequently um perhaps
different data sets maybe using Okay. No
matter what we do more than ever too.
>> Yeah. Right. And it doesn't take a
billion dollars. So then I would take
that billion dollars and put it into the
some of uh plug for Stanford research on
some of the research that we have going
on at the institute thinking about
education and scientific discovery and
some of these uh areas that we think are
going to be very um important. Um but
yeah, I think on the report side, some
of the billion dollars to um generate
more robust data sets, there's still a
lot of data that we can't get that
doesn't exist, especially um one chapter
that has big gaps is in education. It is
very difficult to measure how we are
teaching AI around the globe. um and
>> education of AI or AI educating humans
>> education of AI but yeah there's still
nuance there is um
>> tell me more so what what are the gaps
that you perceive in measuring education
of AI
>> yeah so one of the data points that we
look at in the AI index is um how people
are learning about AI around the globe
uh when the index started we met and
still which is the gap is we measured um
CS education in K12 secondary now that
is um
the data that we have it does not
accurately reflect the state of the
field and it's very difficult to get
data um from around the globe
>> okay so so this does sound then like
education of humans not education of AI
>> yes correct
>> got it okay there's an irony somewhere
in that I I I think if I understand the
history correctly that you started out
with a mandate to measure AI and turns
out AI is making such fast progress
there's no maybe relatively little
marginal point in measuring the AI so
you're turning around and measuring the
humans instead
>> that I like that framing it's
interesting framing yes
>> okay so what do we need to measure about
humans then is the is the end goal is
the is the end intent that you want to
ensure maybe at some latent level the
human economy remains coupled with the
AI. So, and and if that's the case, what
is it that we should be measuring and
optimizing on the human side given that
AI is recursively self-improving?
>> Um, good question. Uh
so that is so this idea of how AI AI is
augmenting humans is something like even
some of our economist we have um an
economist Eric Benjolson at Stanford and
one of the computer scientists D Yang is
looking at like how there's been some
work out of anthropic too on how humans
are using AI to augment themselves in
this human AI coupling um
>> symbiotic relationship with technology.
>> Yeah. Exactly. and and there's you know
micro studies around but having a
broader view of what is working in that
space what is not and how we can really
optimize for the
>> here Alex let me ask you a question yeah
can you ask her something really
ambitious
>> well ambitious is so subjective these
days isn't it
maybe let me ask you a microeconomics
question
>> I'm not any funny
>> I think you are though I I think you're
an economist in disguise now everyone is
everything with AI.
>> Everyone's everything. And in
particular, now that you're it sounds
like turning around and studying the
human economy and less the AI, you've
become an economist. Congratulations.
Dismal science. So, an ambitious
question.
What is the right way to measure real
wealth growth in the human economy as a
result of super intelligence?
>> I don't know. I'm going to pass on that
one. I don't want to be recorded.
>> You wanted me to ask you. Well, so why
don't you say what you think might be
beneficial as they're constructing the
future of this and then you could react
to it. Okay. I think you're measuring
the wrong thing.
>> I think I some of this is is maybe
obvious from some of my earlier somewhat
leading questions. I think we already
have pretty amazing ways although they
have obvious flaws to measure AI
capabilities improvements. I like the
direction I'm hearing on measuring the
human side or what what's left of uh
humanity as currently constructed
interacting with AI. I think the single
biggest gap that I I off the top of my
head that your index could solve is
solving the problem of real wealth
creation. So right now there are
forecasts from some who say real wealth
is going to skyrocket as a result of the
singularity and super intelligence.
We're going to see the economy triple
year overyear. The problem is we don't
really have good ways to measure the
size of the real economy. We have GDP
nominal and real. We have other
macroeconomic measures, but arguably
those go haywire in the presence of true
abundance. So the the challenge that the
recommendation maybe call to greatness I
would have is assume that measures of AI
capabilities are thoroughly cooked. This
is a solved problem. We know how to
measure AI capabilities. Maybe there are
flaws in methodologies, but it's it's
not profoundly difficult enough to merit
an entire Stanford program, but what we
don't have a great measure for is what's
going on in the human economy
interacting with the AI. And my my call
here would be solve that. We need
something better than real GDP.
>> So, um I mentioned Eric Prolson. He I
know.
>> Yeah. Uh you should talk to him about
this. Uh he does have a project called
GDPB. um where they're looking at the
value of digital goods in the economy.
Have you have seen
>> I've seen it. I've read his papers.
>> Okay. So anyway, so that is maybe one
direction. I'm sure he has many other
thoughts, but
>> so just in conclusion,
um [clears throat]
governments are being tracked right now
on how they're approaching AI. There's a
lot of comparisons between China and the
US.
Uh I know your program is not just
getting to the world leaders but the
people
working with the world leaders to help
their respective countries work with AI.
What are you tracking terms of sovereign
AI and um are we going to have some
examples of countries that are having
some success that everyone may copy or
having some challenges that everyone may
may run? um or anything you want to add
to that? I'm I'm thinking about the the
government sovereign AI uh question cuz
I feel like they've gone deep on that
one. It's a troubling issue. I I'm not
sure whether it's as quantitative as one
might like for indexing purposes, but do
you maintain at the level of nation
states an index of call it national
instruments of power or state
capability, state capacity for super
intelligence?
>> Um I wouldn't say super intelligence. We
do try to get data from many countries
around the world on various parts of the
AI stack. I would say from uh their
model development, uh the talent within
the country, uh the compute within the
country. Um and so that is kind of where
we are measuring it right now. Um we did
have a section in the AI index this
year. It was more of a qualitative
highlight section around AI sovereignty
because that phrase is not well defined
at the moment. Um, our policy team also
released a report on kind of like how
people are talking about AI sovereignty
right now and what does that mean and
what do they really want? Um, and can it
be solved by other mechanisms. Um, and
so this is something that we are looking
at and thinking about how we might
measure. Again, historically it was we
were talking kind of these different
aspects that we are now thinking about
holistically as AI sovereignty. So maybe
this year.
>> Well, follow-up question. Both the Biden
and Trump administration by suppressing
Nvidia chips to China. It allowed China
to find more efficient open- source
models. And I'm wondering, did you see
that data coming? And are there going to
be other things like that that you may
be able to see before they go
mainstream? I don't know. Is that a good
question?
>> Sure.
>> May. It sounds like a maybe. I so I
wouldn't say we saw the data in the
report for that but it does bring up
questions about the um effectiveness of
export controls and and how we should be
thinking about those. Um
uh one area that I thought was quite
interesting in this report this year is
we had new data from a company called
Zei that tracks AI talent around the
world. So these are um people who have
AI research publications or AI patents
um and the uh inflow and outflow to and
from different countries. Um inflow of
AI talent into the US dropped by 80% in
the past uh few year or yeah few years
I'm forgetting the exact numbers but um
the chart is is very down. Um India is
almost the exact opposite. the inflow of
talent into India is um significantly
increasing and so that is something to
think about if if different as part of
this AI sovereignty you need the talent
to build the models and to um uh
discover new algorithms and new new ways
and on the hardware and software side
and um these talent trends could be sort
of indicator
>> and and anyone can work with the AI to
do things So just counting bodies isn't
isn't going to get you there.
>> I think it's the innovation is the Yeah.
>> So maybe closing question on my side.
How soon until you have to release a
daily report?
>> I think that that could have happened if
we had uh
>> a billion dollars.
>> I don't think we need a billion dollars,
>> but um if we had Yeah, there's, you
know, checking the data, making sure the
data is sh just because you have data
doesn't mean it's showing the thing that
you want it to show. Um so there's a lot
um upstream in traditional data science
fields around before you can actually
run the analysis.
>> This is what AI is good at. So so
another call to
>> collect the data. Anyway, it's
>> the the Fed releases GDP now several
times per month. I I would love to see a
real-time index of super intelligence
from your program.
>> All right.
>> So last question. Um every uh spring
students graduate from universities and
colleges. If uh a student were to read
your report, what would it say they
should be doing with their lives?
>> So, I'm not sure the report would say
this from a perspective
>> 20 something gain from it as a way to
kind of understand how to optimize.
>> Um I would say seeing what is um
providing again perspective on what has
happened and not getting caught up in
some of the hype that we see in the
news. um but also seeing what is coming.
So this year we had a um there's been an
evolution over a few years. So about
three years ago we we have a tech
performance chapter. In that chapter we
started including uh innovations on the
science and medicine side just kind of
highlights. Um two years ago we broke
that out because we saw so much progress
there into a science and medicine
chapter specifically because we said
there's so much going on here it
deserves its own chapter. This past
year, the 2026 report, we broke them out
into separate chapters. We now have a
science and medicine chapter because
both fields are just again accelerating.
So, kind of being able to see how things
are evolving within the index is um
perhaps maybe parallel to what's
happening in in the
>> we're both all three of us are going to
be at Davos at the world economics.
>> That's the plan.
>> Uh and in that dome, we have the MIT
Cale and Stanford hi collaboration.
Let's get together and do an update on
uh on
>> an update on this few months from now.
This needs to be daily.
>> I know, but I only have the dome in in
January. But but these human
constraints,
>> we'll continue this.
>> This is why we have AI. The the irony is
an AI index that's not using very much
AI.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um thank you Vanessa for
your work and thank you for taking the
time today. Thank you.
>> Thank you.